Finding aid to the Howard Rollin Patch papers. CA.MS.01141
Smith College Archives
Howard Rollin Patch papers
1914-2009
Smith College Archives
Patch, Howard Rollin, 1889-1963
CA.MS.01141
0.667 linear feet (2 containers)
Contains correspondence, photographs, news articles, and publications by Howard Rollin Patch, professor of English, 1919-1957.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source unknown.
Biographical / Historical
Howard Rollin Patch was born in Lake Linden, Michigan, in 1889 to Emily I White and Maurice B. Patch. Patch attended Hobart College in Geneva, New York, until he graduated in 1910. Patch completed his graduate work first at Harvard University, where he received his A.M. in 1912 and his Ph.D. in 1915. In 1924, he received an honorary doctorate of Letters from Hobart College. Patch worked for a number of years as an instructor and lecturer for Harvard (1912-1916), Radcliffe (1915-1916), and Bryn Mawr (1916-1919), before coming to Smith College to teach English in 1919, where he taught medieval literature. At Smith, Patch wrote a large number of articles and books, becoming one of the leading Chaucer scholars in the world. He was a member of the Medieval Academy of America, the Modern Languages Association, Phi Beta Kappa, the Modern Humanities Research Association, the Dante Society, and the Society for the Study of Medieval languages and Literature. Patch married Helen K. Patch, with whom he had four children: Howard R. Patch Jr, Robert K. Patch, Priscilla E. Patch, and Mary (Patch) Coit. He was very active in the Catholic Church, and became a Tertiary of the Order of St. Dominic. He retired in 1957 and died six years later in 1963 in Wellesley, Massachusetts.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains the professional papers and biographical material of Howard Rollin Patch. These papers include professional correspondence to other scholars and to publishers, photographs, and news clippings about Patch's life and publications. The collection also contains 0.50 linear feet of publications by Patch, both academic and fictional.
Smith College -- Faculty; English literature--Study and teaching; Patch, Howard Rollin, 1889-1963; Patch, Howard Rollin, 1889-1963
- General, 1930-2009 (Box 965, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1924-1939 (Box 965, Folder 2)
- Retirement, 1957 (Box 965, Folder 3)
- Photographs, no date (Box 965, Folder 4)
- Publications, no date (Box 966, Folder 1)
- The Academic Slant, no date (Box 966, Folder 2)
- Bibliography of Middle English Dialects, 1923 (Box 966, Folder 3)
- Characters in Medieval Literature, 1925 (Box 966, Folder 4)
- And Where Are We Now?, 1949 (Box 966, Folder 5)
- Chaucer and the Common People, 1930 (Box 966, Folder 6)
- Chaucer and Medieval Romance, 1926 (Box 966, Folder 7)
- Chaucer's Desert, 1919 (Box 966, Folder 8)
- A Collaborative History of Medieval Arthurian Literature, no date (Box 966, Folder 9)
- Consulatio Philosophiae, IV, m. vi. 23-24, 1933 (Box 966, Folder 10)
- Desiderata in Middle English, 1924 (Box 966, Folder 11)
- Do You Know What You Have?, 1951 (Box 966, Folder 12)
- Forty years of Teaching English, no date (Box 966, Folder 13)
- Fortune's Wheel and Boethius, 1914 (Box 966, Folder 14)
- Geoffrey Chaucer and Youth, 1949 (Box 966, Folder 15)
- The Goddess Fortuna in Medieval Literature, 1928-1939 (Box 966, Folder 16)
- The Goddess Fortuna in the Divine Comedy, 1916 (Box 966, Folder 17)
- The Historical Jesus, no date (Box 966, Folder 18)
- In Deep Water, 1957 (Box 966, Folder 19)
- The Lamp of Undying Fire, no date (Box 966, Folder 20)
- The Individual and the Type in Medieval Literature, 1954 (Box 966, Folder 21)
- The Last Line of the Comedia, 1939 (Box 966, Folder 22)
- Liberty, Totality, Sorority, or Lady Macbeth in Northamsk, 1936 (Box 966, Folder 23)
- Liturgical influence in the Dream of the Road, 1919 (Box 966, Folder 24)
- The Ludus Coventriae and the Digby Massacre, 1920 (Box 966, Folder 25)
- Mr. Blanshford Goes to Heaven, 1948 (Box 966, Folder 26)
- Modern Humanism, 1929 (Box 966, Folder 27)
- Necessity of Beethius and the Neoplatonists, 1935 (Box 966, Folder 28)
- Notes on Spenser and Chaucer, 1918 (Box 966, Folder 29)
- The Other World– Correspondence, 1950-1959 (Box 966, Folder 30)
- On Rereading Chaucer - Correspondence, 1941-1950 (Box 966, Folder 31)
- Some Elements in Medieval Descriptions of the Otherworld, 1918 (Box 966, Folder 32)
- A Sarabande For a Poet, no date (Box 966, Folder 33)
- Selections from Chaucer – Correspondence, 1921 (Box 966, Folder 34)
- Cupid on the Stairs, 1943 (Box 966, Folder 35)
- Six Easy and Pleasant Ways to Get Rid of Your Religion, 1956 (Box 966, Folder 36)
- Sweeter Incense, 1937 (Box 966, Folder 37)
- Symbolism of the Supernatural in the Divine Comedy, 1957 (Box 966, Folder 38)
- The Tradition of Boethius – Correspondence, 1938-1939 (Box 966, Folder 39)
- The Road Home, no date (Box 966, Folder 40)
- Triolus on Determination, 1931 (Box 966, Folder 41)
- Troilus on Predestination, 1918 (Box 966, Folder 42)
- What Do You Have?, 1932 (Box 966, Folder 43)
- What the Heathen are Up To, 1953 (Box 966, Folder 44)
- Reviews on Chaucer, 1960 (Box 966, Folder 45)
- Reviews, 1926-1959 (Box 966, Folder 46)